A Guide to the Papers of the Aylett Family, ca. 1851-1896
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Aylett Family ca. 1851-1896
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
110
The collection includes 21 notebooks kept by Aylett while a student at the University of Virginia (1850-1854), and manuscripts of 19 speeches (1851-1854) delivered mainly to the Jefferson Society at the University, the Sons of Temperance and the Young Men's Literary Society.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the library by the Aylett family of Tappahannock, Virginia, on September 7, 1938.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains twenty-one notebooks kept by William Roane Aylett while a student at the University of Virginia, 1850-1854, together with nineteen speeches delivered to various student societies and an essay on University life. Family financial papers chiefly concern the settlement of Philip Aylett's estate, ca.1852-1855, and Judith P. Aylett's guardianship of minor children.
There are also include two notebooks kept by William's son Philip at the Virginia Military Institute, 1884-1888; an undated notebook on mesozoic flora, perhaps kept by Professor W. M. Fontaine at the University of Virginia, 1879-1910; three letters to Fontaine; and a series of clippings and comments on antebellum politics.
Correspondents include Lester F. Ward of the United States Geological Survey and President W. W. Smith of Randolph-Macon College.
Contents List
- Chemistry and Moral Philosophy Notebook 1852 (Box 1)
- French Notebook 1851 (Box 1)
- Geology and Anglo-Saxon Notebook 1851 (Box 1)
- History and Political Economy Notebook 1851 (Box 1)
- Latin Notebook 1854 (Box 1)
- Law Notebook With Constitution and By-Laws of the Jefferson Society 1854 (Box 1)
- Law Notebooks (2 Volumes) 1852-1854 (Box 1)
- Literature of France and Spain Notebook 1851 (Box 1)
- Moral Philosophy Notebook 1852-1853 (Box 1)
- Spanish, Modern History, Natural Philosophy, Ancient History and Anglo-Saxon Notebook n.d. (Box 1)
- Law Notebooks (7 Volumes) 1852-1854 (Box 2)
- Algebra Notebook 1853 (Box 3)
- Law Notebook 1853 (Box 3)
- Trigonometry, Ancient History, Grammar, Latin and Greek Notebook n.d. (Box 3)
- Accounts of Expenses of Philip Aylett at Virginia Military Institute 1884-1888 (Box 3)
- Surveying Notebook of Philip Aylett 1886 (Box 3)
- Mesozoic Flora Notebook Possibly Belonging to Prof. W.M. Fontaine n.d. (Box 3)
- Letters to W.M. Fontaine 1886-1887 (Box 3)
- News Clipping ca. 1896 (Box 4)
- Financial Papers, Writings and Notes, Chiefly re the Settlement of the Estate of Philip Aylett, died ca. 1852 1853-1889, n.d. (Box 4)
- Speeches of W.R. Aylett 1851-1857, n.d.
  - "Heads and Chief Points of a Speech on Women's Influence Upon Civilization" 1851 (Box 4)
  - "Abstract of Speech Given to Jefferson Society" 1851 Oct. 19 (Box 4)
  - "Temperance" 1852, 1853, (3 Speeches) (Box 4)
  - "The Influence of Our Pacific Possessions Upon Our Prosperity and Upon the World's Civilization" 1853, 1854, (2 Speeches) (Box 4)
  - "The Case of Bacon vs. Freeman", As Given To Moot Court at U.Va. 1853 (Box 4)
  - "The Relative Importance of Commerce and Agriculture" 1854, (3 Speeches) (Box 4)
  - "Valedictory Speech to the Jefferson Society" 1854 (Box 4)
  - Speech Before the Young Men's Literary Society 1857 (Box 4)
  - Speech n.d. (Box 4)
  - Speech to Literary Organization n.d. (Box 4)
  - "Are the Commercial Interests of Our Country Superior to the Agricultural?" n.d. (Box 4)
  - "Poetry vs. History" n.d. (Box 4)
  - Series of Resolutions with J.G. Compton n.d. (Box 4)
  - Misc. Parts of Speeches n.d. (Box 4)
  - Speech to Jefferson Society n.d. (Box 4)